Guide to the Benjamin M. Page Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Benjamin M. Page papers
1929-1996
SC0414
Page, Benjamin M. (Benjamin Markham), 1911-
51 Linear feet
Papers include correspondence, minutes, budgets, class notes, course files, student papers, reports, maps, and research files and pertain to his activities as professor, department administrator, and scientist. Some papers relate to his work with the Advisory Committee on Reactor Safeguards (AEC/NRC). There are also papers relating to the geological investigation of the site for the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center; photographs from geology trips, 1930-1953, including the department's summer geology field classes, 1941 and 1946-49; and an album of photo negatives from Page's student days, 1929-32, on hiking/camping trips, geology trips, other students, and his dorm room.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Benjamin M. Page, 1991; and transfer from Dept. of Geology, 1997-2000.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Geologist. Page, a member of the Stanford class of 1933, also earned his master's degree in 1934 and his Ph.D in 1940 at Stanford. He joined the Stanford faculty in 1943, becoming full professor in 1952; he was head of the Geology Department from 1957-62 and again from 1965-68. He retired in 1976. Page's special fields are structural geology and the relationship between geological structures and plate tectonics.
Description of the Collection
Papers include correspondence, minutes, budgets, class notes, course files, student papers, reports, maps, and research files and pertain to his activities as professor, department administrator, and scientist. Some papers relate to his work with the Advisory Committee on Reactor Safeguards (AEC/NRC). There are also papers relating to the geological investigation of the site for the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center; photographs from geology trips, 1930-1953, including the department's summer geology field classes, 1941 and 1946-49; and an album of photo negatives from Page's student days, 1929-32, on hiking/camping trips, geology trips, other students, and his dorm room.
Access Terms
Page, Benjamin M. (Benjamin Markham), 1911-; Stanford Linear Accelerator Center; Stanford University. Department of Geology. Faculty.; Stanford University. Department of Geology.; U.S. Atomic Energy Commission. Advisory Committee on Reactor Safequards.; Geology--Study and teaching (higher).; Photoprints.; Plate tectonics; Topographical surveying.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-1999-009
  - Brittain, J.H. and J.R. Boyle. Earth Movement and Geodetic Control for Stanford Linear Accelerator Center. (Box 1)
  - Dames & Moore. Geotechnical Investigation, Proposed Positron-Electron Project: Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, Stanford, California. (Box 1)
  - Dickinson, B.W.O. Design Study and Cost Estimates for Stanford University Project "M". (Box 1)
  - Earth Sciences Associates. Geotechnical Site Investigation of Regions 11, 12, 1, 2 and 3: Positron Electron Project (PEP). (Box 1)
  - PEP Site Exploratory Drilling, 1975 Program: Summary Logs of Borings (2 copies) (Box 1)
  - Skjei, R.E. et al. Geologic Site Investigation for Stanford Linear Accelerator Center. (Box 1)
  - Trask, Parker D. Engineering Geology Proposed Linear Electron Accelerator, Sand Hill Site, Stanford, University, California. (Box 1)
  - SLAC—Geologic Maps (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - SLAC—Field Notes, 1963-64 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - SLAC—Correspondence and Notes for Article, 1965-78 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - SLAC—Dibblee's Map (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - SLAC—References, Abstracts and References (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - SLAC—Notes: Rocks (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - SLAC—Tabor's Maps and Notes, 1962-65 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - SLAC—Air Photos with Geologic Notations, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - SLAC—Project "M" (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - SLAC—Site Investigation: Correspondence, Reports, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - SLAC—Photos by Ben Page and L. Tabor (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - SLAC—Geophysical and Geodetic Data (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - SLAC—PEP Ring, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - SLAC—SLC (Stanford Linear Collider) 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - SLAC—Notes and Articles, 1980s-90s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Crustal Structure—Seismic Velocities (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Crustal Structure—pre-1990s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Crustal Structure—papers by Brocher and Holbrook, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Crustal Structure—papers and notes, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - California Tectonics—Salinian B. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - California Tectonics—Temblor Range and Carizzo Plain (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Tectonics of West Coast, GSA 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Pseudosubduction: Change in Plate Motions (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Tectonics of Coast Ranges—Correspondence and Notes (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Tectonics of Coast Ranges—Manuscript and Ideas (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Tectonics of Coast Ranges—Draft, 11/22/96 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Tectonics of Coast Ranges—Submitted Draft, 11/25/96 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Appendices (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Quantifying Anderson's Fault Types," Simpson, Robert W. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - CR Uplift—Compression Normal to San Andreas Fault (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - CR Uplift--References (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - CR Uplift—Info: Abstracts, Sources, Notes (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - CR Uplift—Info: Reprints, Preprints (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - CR Uplift—Tables (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Rise of Ranges—Backlog/Back-up Material (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Rise of Ranges—Figures for M.S. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Rise of Ranges—Fluid Pressure, Mechanics and Seismicity (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Rise of Ranges—Folds and Faults (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Rise of Ranges—Geomorphology (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Rise of Ranges—Gravity, Magnetics, Etc. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Rise of Ranges—Heat Flow (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Rise of Ranges—Marine Terraces and Piercement Structures (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Rise of Ranges—Marginal and Nearby Faults (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Rise of Ranges—Papers (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Rise of Ranges—Plio-Pleist Formations (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Rise of Ranges—Recent Work/Information (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Rise of Ranges—Shortening, Transverse (Part I) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Rise of Ranges—Shortening, Transverse (Part II) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Rise of Ranges—Uplift (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Rise of Ranges—Wedges, Blind Thrusts and Active Folds (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Rise of Ranges—Xenoliths in C2 Volcanoes (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Articles—Life-Origins, Extinctions, Etc. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Articles—Man: Prognosis, Geological History (Part I) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Articles—Man: Prognosis, Geological History (Part II) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Articles—General: A-C (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Articles—General: D-F (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Articles—General: G-L (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Articles—General: M-N (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Articles—General: P-Y (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Fault-Lake Seismic Reflection Project (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Geologic Guides and Tools (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Geology/Geophysics: Instruments, Techniques (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Palaeoparadoxia (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Radioactive Waste Disposal (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "Stepovers of Motion" (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Super-Collider: Recent Information (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Atilla Ayadin, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: General (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Notes and Articles—Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Photos: Oso Cr. Near Cachuma Reservoir, Santa Barbara Co. (Box 8)
  - American Geophysical Union. Selected Papers on the Toa Baja Drilling Project, Puerto Rico. (Box 8)
  - Durham, David L. Geology of the Tierra Redona Mountain and Bradley Quadrangles Monterey and San Luis Obispo Counties, California. (Box 8)
  - Hall, Clarence A., Jr. Geology and Paleontology of the Pleasonton Area, Alameda and Contra Costa Counties, California. (Box 8)
  - U.S. Department of Energy, Nuclear Waste Policy Act. Progress Report on the Scientific Investigation Program for the Nevada Yucca Mountain Site. (Box 8)
  - Woodward-Clyde Consultants. Review of the Pacific Northwest Earthquake of December 14, 1872. (Box 8)
  - Metal Notebook with Leather Pencil Pouch (Box 9)
  - Cardboard Global Reference Frame (Box 9)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2002-019
  Album was received without negatives in envelopes numbered 29, 63, 65, 80, 82, 87, 89, 92, 96, 97, 99, 100
  - Photographs
    - Arizona, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Assorted locations: Wheeler Ridge, CA, 1948; Old Woman Mountains, CA; near Crystal Lake, 1938; near Ventura, 1938; Shelton & Sumpfs area, 1940; Paloma Creek; Humboldt Mountains; Sonora Range (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Berkeley area (Claremont chert), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Candelaria, NV, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Candelaria, NV - negatives 1939, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Candelaria, NV, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Candelaria, NV, - negatives, probably 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Candelaria, NV, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Candelaria, NV, no date (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - near Clear Lake, no date (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Darwin, March 1942 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Darwin to Death Valley, Feb. 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Death Valley 1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Edna, CA, tar sands, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Ganim mine, July 1942 (includes Ganim house, Joseph S. Ganim, and group of Ben Page, Lauren Wright, and Ganim (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Gold Field, NV, Nov. 1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Keeler oasis, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Leavenworth (WA), area I and II (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Leavenworth (WA), area IV (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Leavenworth (WA), area V and VI (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Leavenworth (WA), area VIII (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Leavenworth (WA), miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Leavenworth (WA), illustration of lateral moraine of Leavenworth stage (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Leavenworth (WA), assorted images, mostly not labeled, 1939 and no date (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Leavenworth (WA), area – negatives, probably of Leavenworth area (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Negatives, without prints [wharf at ocean, group of 7 men, train at Sierra Talc Company, 2 illustrations, and 3 images of children] (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Nevada, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - New Mexico trip, May-June 1942 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Panamint Mountains, ca. 1930 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Point Arena (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Santa Cruz area, 1944 (includes images of men surveying (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Santa Ynez, summer 1947 – with captions (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Santa Ynez, summer 1947 – no captions or duplicates (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Santa Ynez, summer 1947 – negatives (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Summer Geology, 1941 (Idaho) and undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Summer Geology, 1946 – Arroyo Seco (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Summer Geology, 1946 – Arroyo Seco, duplicate images (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Summer Geology, 1946 – Arroyo Seco, no number, no caption (print and negative) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Summer Geology, 1946 – Arroyo Seco, negatives (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Summer Geology, 1946 – Nevada (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Summer Geology, 1947 – Nevada, Summit King area (includes 2 images of the group) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Summer Geology, 1948 – Nevada and unspecified (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Summer Geology, 1948 (possibly – images of Reliz Canyon and Arroyo Seco) (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Summer Geology, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Superior Talc Mine, Sierra Nevada near Independence, White Eagle Mine, 1942 (includes image of Lauren Wright with other people) (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Talc, assorted images, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Talc City Mine, Inyo County, CA, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Talc City Mine, negatives of maps and illustrations (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Tar sands (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Tioga Pass, White Mountain Mine, July-Aug. 1942; includes image of Lauren Wright and survey car (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Utah, near Zion Canyon, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Wright, Lauren, at White Eagle Mine, May 1942 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Yosemite Falls, dry season, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Album of negatives from Page's student years (labeled No. V), 1929-1932, with index. Appear to be from summer geology trips and camping/hiking trips, along with images of students and his Encina dorm room. Prints from four negatives (#60a and b, #61, #62) have been added to GP (#16073-16076). (Box 5, Folder 9)